hi and welcome back to another video
with it's Dr Dan and today we're going
to be looking at the world of solubility
so in this video I'm going to go over
the basics of how we can actually see
how different materials when they're
added to a liquid such as water how
exactly are they going to behave how are
they going to be breaking apart when
you're looking at these especially
leading up to net ionic reactions which
show how different ions come together
and actually dissociate in water so
let's take a look at it and try to see
what does solubility have to talk about
and really what the world of solutions
is all about
[Music]
thank you so in the very beginning when
we look at any of these things
what we are trying to understand is how
does a solution necessarily behave
so at the very start what it kind of
looks like is let's say if you take salt
table salt and you add it to a pot of
water for example if you're going to
make pasta or rice well what's exactly
going to be happening to it when you add
it into that pot well first you're going
to see salt sitting right at the bottom
of that vessel and until you Stir It Up
it doesn't necessarily dissolve so what
is really occurring there well salt is
an ionic compound right sodium chloride
so you have the sodium ions with those
little chlorine ions like how I have
shown here and the way that that's
oriented is in a lattice now how does it
dissolve what is happening especially
when we compare if I put hundreds and
thousands of water molecules all around
it well what are we seeing well once you
start moving this solution around you're
causing random molecular motion to occur
meaning that there's this unpredictable
movement of molecules within this
solution
so when we are looking at this thing
will it dissolve and they're all like
yeah absolutely certain chloride does
dissolve what is this guy talking about
and you're right but what exactly
happens well the way that we can look at
this is when you mix salt and water can
you see the salt anymore once it mixes
and the thing is no you can't right when
you're going through that you made a
homogeneous
solution meaning that it is fully
uniform
when you see it it's no longer you're no
longer able to really be able to see
that difference between the two layers
now in the solution we can label a
couple different things right it's made
of water and salt so this is what we
refer to as an aqueous solution okay so
this is aqueous meaning that
what is the solvent well the solvent in
this case
is water right so that is the major
component of this is solvent
is H2O so whenever something is a
solvent that is the major shareholder in
this particular
um this particular vial that we have
so we have our solvent and we also have
a solute the solute and this can't case
is the smaller component or the minor
portion
in this case it's going to be sodium
chloride
now when water all of a sudden comes
into contact with this per these
particular ions it starts to surround
them and eventually what's going to be
happening well we're going to create
different forces that are going to be
caused here
we're going to have ion dipole
forces forming all around the sodium
chloride and when you add enough water
molecules hundreds or dozens of water
molecules around every single ion it's
eventually going to be pulling them
apart and actually causing it to be
soluble so how can we show these
different reactions well it what we do
is is we do different solubility
equations so being that I have NaCl
uh in solution we can show how that's
going to be breaking down so what
happened we had NaCl
and that was originally a solid
and it was added to water
that's breaking down into two ions that
we have here right we have one n a plus
and one cl minus so it gets dissociated
into each of their individual pieces so
we have n a
plus and then we also have CL
minus as the other part so it
dissociates into its ions now why is
that something that's important well
when you take multiple solutions they
dissolve and you mix them together
that's when certain chemical reactions
are going to start occurring this is
when we can have different aqueous
Solutions in this case so when we have n
a plus this is going to be n a plus
AQ
and cl minus AQ telling you that they're
both aqueous within solution we're going
to go through a few examples to show
exactly what this represents now are
these only in terms of ions are they the
only things that are going to be
dissociating well are what exactly
dissolves well what if I look at a
different example of solubility what if
you take sugar and you throw that into
a glass of water does it dissolve and
you're gonna be like well okay it's not
ionic sugar is a
c6h1206 I have the little structure here
if I were to put all those within a vial
what is that exactly going to look like
you're going to have all these sugar
molecules are going to be close together
but then all of a sudden they're going
to be wandering and dispersing apart
they're going to randomly move away from
each other so what exactly happens with
these Solutions the first thing that we
got to remember is an old phrase of ours
which is like dissolves like
so in this case what does that mean well
water
is a polar molecule
so what would water dissolve well it's
going to dissolve
other polar molecules like dissolves
like so in this case when we have
glucose
glucose over here is this molecule down
here and we can copy and paste that up
here for ourselves
and when we actually see that thing well
it is
C6H12O6 but notice how it has a bunch of
oh groups all around them
these are all polar groups
so being a therapolar they're going to
dissolve how can we try to show that how
can we illustrate that these dissolve
well
for us it's actually once again we're
going to write a solubility equation to
show this so if I take C6 h12
o6 and it's a solid sugar cube that I'm
adding to water is it going to
dissociate an ionize no not in this case
because it's not made of ionic materials
instead when we add that to water it's
going to just be
C6H12O6 and we're going to label it as
aqueous meaning that it dissolved so it
you can't see it it's still a
homogeneous mixture but it didn't
actually break apart and ionize
so and that's kind of the idea behind a
lot of these so these are the two major
types so this is ionic and covalent so
when you are trying to do these a lot of
them tend to be with ionic molecules
covalent follows just the light
dissolves-like rule
when you are looking at the two types so
when it comes to solubility with ionic
compounds there are a set of rules that
we use solubility tables to determine if
something is soluble so when we're
looking at these the way that my chart
here works is the top is always soluble
except when it's bound to certain ions
and the bottom on the black area down
here is always insoluble all the time
except when it's bound to certain
certain individual ions so we're going
to be practicing using solubility rules
and actually going through the different
types of solubility equations that you
can see now if something is insoluble
meaning it won't break down what it's
going to be forming is something known
as a precipitate a precipitate is an
insoluble substance that separates from
the solution so meaning it stays as a
solid so we're going to be looking at
some of these different examples and
really how we can showcase them
practicing using solubility rules so
let's try the very first one so let's
say I have KCl
now KCl when I add that to a to water
what exactly is going to happen so what
we're going to look at is look for the
two individual ions
so the ions are going to be k
and cl
so what would that dissociate into be K
plus and cl minus
let's see if it's soluble do we have
those two individual ions here
so if we look here we can see that
alkali metals which is the very first
one up here are always soluble and we
can see K plus right here so that's
letting you know yes this is soluble so
what this reaction tells you is
absolutely this is this one is going to
be soluble
so the way that we can illustrate that
is by putting AQ next to both of our
ions here telling you yes this one is
soluble
what if we try another what if I have n
a 3po4
po4 here and now with this one how would
this one break apart now the whole idea
with this is it is all the ions are
getting fully surrounded by water so
when this breaks down we're going to be
making
sodium which is one of our ions
and po4 which is our other ion so when
we write this we write n a plus
po43 minus
and being that there is if you notice
here like oh shouldn't I include the
subscript and you're right
but what that subscript tells you is
that there's three sodiums bound around
one phosphate so in a sense it's kind of
like saying all right if I have po4
3 minus
I have
all these sodiums that are completely
surrounding
um
that phosphate so it's like having three
of them
bound around on all sides
now being the I have three of those
individual ions they all fully
dissociate
so when that happens one way for us to
kind of to sort of look at that is well
all right if I have
all of these little um
these uh
these water molecules surrounding this
little these sodiums here well I can
kind of draw that here and write okay I
have a sodium in the middle and that's
going to be surrounded by
sodiums on all parts so we can
illustrate that for ourselves
so when we have that we have multiple
sodiums being surrounded by water on all
sides
okay and then we also have our other one
all right so when this thing dissociates
it's the same thing as saying that we
have the three sodiums
surrounded by water on all sides
and then we also have the phosphate as
well being surrounded
so when we want to make sure this is a
balanced chemical equation we want to
show that we have three sodiums one
phosphate now let's check is it even
soluble to begin with
so sodium is also one of our alkali
metals so one thing you can always
remember what is always soluble which is
the abbreviation Anna meaning alkali
metals ammonium nitrate acetates are
always soluble no matter what so in this
case we see that sodium is one of our
alkali metals this is always going to be
soluble you can also look at nitrates as
well or sorry you can look at phosphates
too and being that we have a phosphate
down here phosphate is insoluble except
when it's bound to an anomolecule so in
this case it is going to be soluble and
you can look up either ion they they
don't contradict each other as long as
you can find one of them on this chart
it will obey that rule
okay so being at that is soluble we will
write a q
next to each of these individual pieces
here
let's do another so what if I gave you
the following what if I gave you acetic
acid
so c2h3o2
and I had this liquid here and I'm going
to throw that into water what is going
to be happening so we have to once again
go through the two individual pieces
here and try to separate the ions so one
of them is the acetate ion
which is
c2h3o2 that has a negative ion and then
h plus on both sides so this is going to
be h plus
C2
h3o2 minus
are these soluble so what we either look
is either for the hydrogen ion or the
acetate ion
so we can see that the acetate ion is
one of our always soluble species here
so we can notice that right here acetate
is always soluble no matter what so in
this case it's going to be soluble so
let's fill that in so we're going to
write that as aqueous for both parts of
the reaction
what if we do another one let's do two
more just to kind of wrap it all up so
what if I gave you calcium
carbonate
would this be soluble
in water
so the things that we're going to be
looking in are going to be calcium
and carbonate now when we look at both
of these one thing we're looking for is
either ion and one thing you might find
really quickly is
here's carbonate down here at the bottom
notice how it's in the soluble so being
that this is insoluble
and there's no exceptions to that at all
except when it is bound to Anna
that is the only time that that is ever
insoluble
or sorry soluble so being that this is
insoluble all the time
this is going to stay as a solid so how
do we write that well being that this is
insoluble it's going to stay as a solid
and we can just write insoluble next to
it and that would be
our answer is that it's insoluble and as
simple as that you're looking to see
what are the ions making up each of
these parts
what about barium
sulfate what about this when we're
adding barium sulfate to water how could
we illustrate that particular example
so once again we're either going to look
for barium two plus or sulfate 2 minus
and if we look up barium sulfate one
thing you can see is okay sulfates are
soluble
which we have here
except when they're bound to Barium so
that is the exception here so being that
it's bound to Barium that tells you even
though sulfates are always soluble it's
bound to Barium making it insoluble so
with barium sulfate this one is also
insoluble it won't break together or
break apart and an interesting fact
about barium sulfate this is actually
one of the contrast agents that's
commonly used in x-rays to actually try
to boost X-rays and that's one of the
reasons why they want to use this
because it's insoluble it'll help
actually coat parts of the body so that
way it contrasts your bones and makes
them a little bit more visible you don't
want also want barium to be dissolving
in the body because barium is extremely
toxic as an ionic form so being it's
insoluble it's safe to adjust in small
amounts when it comes to medical imaging
so a lot of these things have different
purposes when it comes to the Health
Sciences specifically so that's just one
of these examples so this is the basic
idea of how to go through looking at
solubility
mainly what we're trying to do is see
what ions does it dissolve into then
we're going through the solubility rules
to see how that break apart breaks apart
and what this going to feed into is
looking at aqueous reactions or
precipitation reactions to see okay if I
have two of these Solutions and I mix
them together will this actually make a
solid or will they all dissolve and be
no reaction all right and then this is
my video on looking at solubility and I
hope that this helped a little bit and I
hope to see you all in the future later
all right bye now hope you all have a
wonderful day
foreign